Alright, this is CS50
Harvard University's Introduction to the intellectual enterprises of computer science
and the arts of programming
Back here on campus and beautiful Sanders Theatre for the first time in quite a while
So, welcome to the class
My name is David Malan, again
So my name is David Malan
and I took this class myself some time ago
but almost did it
It was sophomore fall
and I was sitting in on the class
and I was a little curious
didn't really feel like the field for me
I was definitely a computer person
but computer science felt like something altogether
And I only got up the nerve to take the class ultimately
because the professor at the time
Brian Kernighan
allowed me to take the class pass-fail, initially
And that is what made all the difference
I quickly found that
computer science is not just about programming and working in isolation on your computer
it's really about problem solving, more generally
And there was something about homework, frankly, that was actually fun
for perhaps the first time in what 19 years
and there was something about this ability that I discovered along with all of my classmates
to actually create something and bring a computer to life to solve a problem
and sort of bring to bear something that I'd been using every day
but didn't really know how to harness
that's been gratifying ever since
and definitely challenging and frustrating like to this day, all these years later
you're gonna run up against mistakes
otherwise known as bugs in programming
that just drive you nuts
and you feel like you've hit a wall
but the trick really is to give it enough time, to take a step back
take a break when you need to
And there's nothing better, I dare say
than that sense of gratification and pride really when you get something to work
and in a class like this present ultimately a terms end
something like your very own final project
Now this isn't to say that I took to it 100% perfectly
In fact, just this, this past week
I looked in my old CS50 binder
which I still have from some 25 years ago
and took a photo of what was apparently the very first program that I wrote and submitted
and quickly received -2 points on
But this is a program that we'll soon see in the coming days
that does something quite simply, like print "Hello, CS50!"
in this case, to the screen
And to be fair, I technically hadn't really followed the directions
which is why I lost those couple of points
But if you just look at this
especially if you've never programmed before
you might have heard about programming languages
but you've never typed something like this out
undoubtedly it's going to look cryptic
But unlike human languages, frankly,
which were a lot more sophisticated, a lot more vocabulary, a lot more grammatical rules,
programming, once you start to wrap your mind around what it is and how it works
and what these various languages are,
it's so easy, you'll see after a few months of a class like this, to start teaching yourself subsequently other languages,
as they may come in the coming years as well.
So, what ultimately matters in this particular course
is not so much where you end up relative to your classmates,
but where you end up relative to yourself when you began.
And indeed you'll begin today.
And the only experience that matters ultimately in this class is your own.
And so consider where you are today,
consider perhaps just how cryptic something like that looked a few seconds ago
and take comfort in knowing, just some months from now, all of that will be within your own grasp.
And if you're thinking that,
okay, surely, the person in front of me, to the left, to the right, behind me
knows more than me
that's statistically not the case.
2/3 of CS50 students have never taken a CS course before,
which is to say you're in very good company throughout this whole term.
So, then what is computer science?
I claim that it's problem solving
and the upside of that is that problem solving is something we sort of do all the time
But computer science class
learning to program I think
kind of cleans up your thoughts
It helps you learn how to think more methodically
more carefully, more correctly, more precisely
Because honestly
the computer is not going to do what you want
and unless you are correct and precise and methodical
and so as such
there's these sort of
fringe benefits of just learning to think
like a computer scientist
in the programmer
and it doesn't take all that much to start doing so
This for instance is perhaps the simplest picture of computer science
sure, but really problem solving in general
problems are all about taking input
like the problem you want to solve
you want to get the solution, a.k.a. output
and so something interesting gotta to be happening in here
in here
when you're trying to get from those inputs to output
Now in the world of computers specifically
we need to decide in advance
how we represent these inputs and outputs
we all just need to decide whether it's Mac or PCs or phones or something else
that we're all going to speak some common language
irrespective of our human languages as well
And you may very well know
that computers tend to speak only what language
so to speak
assembly one
but binary too might be your goal too
In "binary", "bi" implying "two" means that the world of computers
has just 2 digits at its disposal, 0 and 1.
And indeed we humans have many more than that
certainly not just zeros and ones alone
but a computer indeed only has zeros and ones
And yet somehow
they can do so much
they can crunch numbers and excels and text messages
create images
and artwork and movies and more
And so how do you get from something as simple as a few zeros a few ones
to all of the stuff that we're doing today in our pockets and laptops and desktops
Well, it turns out that we can start quite simply
if a computer were to want to do something as simple as count
what could it do? While in our human world
we might count doing this like: "1 2 3 4 5"
using so-called unary notation
literally the digits on your fingers
were one figure represents one person in the room
if I'm, for instance, taking attendance
now we humans would typically actually count
1 2 3 4 5 6
and we'd go past just those 5 digits and count much higher
using zeros through nines
but computers somehow only have these zeros and ones
so if a computer only somehow speaks binary zeros and ones
how does it even count past the number one
Well here are 3 zeros, of course,
and if you translate this number in binary "000"
to a more familiar number in decimal
we would just call this 0
enough said
if we were to represent with a computer the number 1
it would actually be 001
which not surprisingly is exactly the same as we might do in our human world
but we might not bother writing out the 2 zeros at the beginning
but a computer now
if it wants to count as high as 2
it doesn't have the digit 2
and so it has to use a different pattern of zeros and ones
and that happens to be "010"
so this is not "10" with a "0" in front of it
it's indeed "010" in the context of binary
and if we want to count higher than 2
we're going to have to tweak these zeros and ones further to get 3
and then if we want 4 or 5 or 6 or 7
we're just kind of toggling these zeros and ones
a.k.a. bits, for binary digits
that represent via these different patterns
different numbers that you and I as humans know, of course, as
the so called decimal system
0 through 9 deck implying 10
10 digits, those zeros through 9
so why that particular pattern
and why these particular zeros and ones
well, turns out that representing one thing or the other
is just really simple for a computer
Why?
At the end of the day, they're powered by electricity
and it's a really simple thing to just either store some electricity or don't store some electricity
like that's as simple as the words can get, "on" or "off"
"1" or "0", so to speak
So, in fact, inside of a computer, a phone, anything these days that's electronic pretty much
is some number of switches
otherwise known as transistors
And they're tiny. You've got thousands, millions of them in your Mac or PC, your phone these days
And these are just tiny little switches that can get turned on and off
and by turning those things on and off in patterns
a computer can count from 0 on up to 7
and even higher than that
And so these switches really you can think of being as
switches like this
let me just borrow one of our little stage lights here
here's a light bulb
it's currently off
and so I could just think of this as representing
in my laptop, that a transistor or a switch representing "0"
but if I allow some electricity to flow
now I in fact have a one
Well how do I count higher than one
of course we need another light bulb
so let me grab another one here
and if I put it in that same kind of pattern
I don't want to just do this
that's sort of the old finger counting way of unary
just one, two
I want to actually take into account the pattern of these things being on and off
so if this was "1" a moment ago
what I think I did earlier was I turned it off